Guide to the Lewis L. Lorwin Papers 1952-1962
Lorwin, Lewis L. Papers
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
Lewis L. Lorwin Papers, 1952-1962
5152
Lorwin, Lewis L.
2 linear ft.
Reports.
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives, Cornell University Library
Consist chiefly of reports and agendas of the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions, correspondence, studies and reports regarding international relations, the world economy and trade unions throughout the world, especially in postwar Europe
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Lewis Lorwin was an economist and labor historian, who over the course of his career, worked as economic advisor to the International Labor Office, the New York State Labor Department, the National Resources Planning Board, and the Foreign Economic Administration. He also held positions at the Brookings Institution and the Office of International Trade of the Department of Commerce.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Consist chiefly of reports and agenda of the International Confederation of Free Trade Unions (ICFTU) held in Brussels and New York, 1949-1962, which deal with nuclear warfare and universal disarmament, World Refugee Year (1959), foreign investments in economically underdeveloped countries, atomic energy, expansion of international trade, married women in employment, foreign assistance to developing countries, fair labor standards in international trade, the European coal and steel community, international migration problems, ICFTU boycott of South Africa, forced labor, workweek, Hungarian people's fight for freedom, the Middle East, and the United Nations. Also materials on Aden, Africa, Algeria, Aruba, Berlin, Brazil, Congo, Costa Rica, Curaao, Cyprus, Dominican Republic, Finland, Greece, Indonesia, Italy, Japan, Korea, Latin America, Lebanon, Netherlands Antilles, Nyasaland, Oceania, Okinawa, Pakistan, Paraguay, Portugal (and the Portuguese colonies), Rhodesia, Spain, Surinam, Thailand, Tibet, Tunisia, Uganda, Venezuela, and West Irian (Dutch New Guinea).
Also copies of letters (l947) from Matthew Woll (vice-president of the American Federation of Labor) to George C. Marshall (secretary of state) regarding the situation in Germany which shut the A.F.of L. off from the French and Russian zones; to Robert P. Patterson (secretary of war) regarding the A.F. of L. protest of the visit of the World Federation of Trade Unions (WFTU) mission to Japan and Korea (with Patterson's reply); to Premier Paul Ramadier regarding the French military government in Germany refusing A.F. of L. representative entry permit into French zones and refusal to accept mail.
Studies and reports concern A.F. of L. union structure (1939), communism in Eastern and Southeastern Europe (1947), trade union government (1961), labor-management relations (1960), trade union issues (1947), labor philosophy (1959), neo-institutionalism and economic change (1965), labor racketeering (1965), wage price guidelines (1966), reconstruction of the international union movement (1949), World Trade Union Conference (1944), coal economy throughout the world (1947), and Congress of Industrial Organizations (CIO) (1948).
Reprints of articles by Lorwin and clippings, news releases, speeches and published articles on the CIO and A.F. of L. abroad, socialism, and communism.
Also scattered holograph notes.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Lorwin, Lewis Levitzki, 1883-1970; Marshall, George C. (George Catlett), 1880-1959; Patterson, Robert P. (Robert Porter), 1891-1952; Ramadier, Paul, 1888-1961; Woll, Matthew, 1880-1956; International Confederation of Free Trade Unions; United Nations; World Federation of Trade Unions.
Subjects:
Atomic weapons and disarmament.; Atomic power--International control.; Nuclear disarmament.; Berlin (Germany)--Politics and government--1945-1990.; Berlin (Germany)--History--1945-1990.; Boycotts--South Africa.; Communism--Europe, Eastern.; Communism--Europe, Southern.; Economic assistance, American.; Forced labor.; Foreign trade and employment.; International economic relations.; International labor activities.; Labor policy--Aden.; Labor policy--Cyprus.; Labor policy--Dominican Republic.; Labor policy--Greece.; Labor policy--Indonesia.; Labor policy--Korea (South); Labor policy--Okinawa Island (Japan); Labor policy--Paraguay.; Labor policy--Rhodesia and Nyasaland.; Labor policy--Thailand.; Racketeering--United States.; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Europe.; Refugees.; Sex discrimination in employment.; Labor unions--Africa.; Labor unions--Algeria.; Labor unions--Aruba.; Labor unions--Brazil.; Labor unions--Costa Rica.; Labor unions--Curaao.; Labor unions--Finland.; Labor unions--Italy.; Labor unions--Japan.; Labor unions--Latin America.; Labor unions--Lebanon.; Labor unions--Near East.; Labor unions--Netherlands Antilles.; Labor unions--Oceania.; Labor unions--Pakistan.; Labor unions--Portugal.; Labor unions--Surinam.; Labor unions--Tunisia.; Labor unions--Uganda.; Labor unions--Venezuela.; Labor unions--Zaire.; Labor unions and communism.; Economists; Coal mining industry. Europe.; Developing countries. Foreign economic relations.; Steel industry. Europe.
Geographic Subjects:
Berlin (Germany) -- History -- 1945-1990; Germany--History--Allied occupation, 1945-; Hungary--History--Revolution, 1956.; Irian Jaya (Indonesia)--Politics and government--To 1963.; Spain--Politics and government--1939-1975.; Tibet (China). Autonomy.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
RELATED MATERIALS
Related Collections:
5582: Archives Foreign File (AFF)
5956: Archives Organization File Additional records
CONTAINER LIST
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 2), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 2), 1952 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 4), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 4), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 3 of 4), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 4 of 4), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 3), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 3), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 3 of 3), 1956 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 3), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 3), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 3 of 3), 1957 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 4), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 4), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 3 of 4), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 4 of 4), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 2), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 2), 1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 2), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 2), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 1 of 2), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes (folder 2 of 2), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- ICTFU Executive Board Minutes, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- AFL Abroad, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Communism, 1956 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Communism (Box 3, Folder 3)
- CIO Abroad, 1947 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- CIO Abroad, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Labor Abroad Miscellaneous (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Labor and The Economic Cooperation Administration (Box 3, Folder 7)
- WFTU (Box 3, Folder 8)
- WFTU - Background and Organization, 1941-1945 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- WFTU Communism (Box 3, Folder 10)
- WFTU, 1945-1948 (Box 3, Folder 11)
- World War II and After, 1939-1951 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- ICFTU Info Bulletin (Box 3, Folder 13)
- Provisonal Report of the 2nd WFTU Enquiry Commission on the Situation in Germany, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  World Federation of Trade Unions. January-February 1947
- Federation of the Coal Industry in the World, 1947 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  Report presented to the Executive Bureau, Executive Committee, and the General Council of the World Federation of Trade Unions. Prague, June 2-14, 1947.
- Columbia University Seminar on Labor, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  March 17, 1965.
- Newsletters, 1957-1971 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Socialist International Information, 1951-1957 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  v.1:no.29-30 (1951: July 21). Includes correspondence from May 13, 1957
- ICFTU Constitution and other publications, 1949-1958 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Third World Trade Union Congress, 1953 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  Vienna, October 10-21, 1953.
- Reprints of Articles by Lewis L. Lorwin and his son Val R. Lorwin, 1936-1953 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- Text digitized from the collection. (Box 5)